# **ESTHER E. BOWLIN**

#### **OBJECTIVE**

Environmental sciences professional experienced in field operations, team leadership, and technical writing. Proficient with geospatial technologies, MS Office software, and environmental remediation projects. Professional interests include geospatial analysis, Python scripting, and GIS web application development.

#### **SKILLS & ABILITIES**

Over three years of environmental sampling experience including long term groundwater monitoring, surface water sampling, and soil sampling. Over three years of professional experience with ESRI's ArcGIS Desktop and over three years of educational experience with GPS technologies and software platforms.

Over two years of experience with state and federal clients including Army Corps of Engineers, State of Colorado, Unites States Air Force, and National Park Service.

Currently training in Python, JavaScript, Angular JS, and HTML 5 programming languages.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

## GIS ANALYST I/GEOPHYSICIST I, HDR, INC.

Centennial, CO

04/2012 - 08/2014

Performed geospatial, geophysical, and environmental duties for private, state, and federal contracts. Created GPS survey plans utilizing ArcGIS Desktop, Pathfinder Office, and BaseCamp software applications, processed geophysical field data, and led environmental sampling teams. Performed right-of-way studies, and contributed to environmental impact assessments for oil and natural gas clients.

Responsible for technical report writing including standard operating procedures, scope of work statements, work plans, EPA compliant work proposals, training materials, and technical guidance documents. Preformed quality assurance/quality control on technical documents produced by environmental staff members.

Participated in Environmental Site Assessment and contaminant removal projects including borehole logging, groundwater sampling, and soil sampling. Responsible for collection of samples, labeling and shipping of samples to testing facilities, and creation cartographic products to support sampling objectives.

### WILDLIFE RANGER, GROUSE MOUNTAIN REFUGE FOR ENDANGERED WILDLIFE

Vancouver, British Columbia

06/2010 - 03/2012

Implemented and enforced public safety measures for visitors and staff regarding environmental protection and wildlife issues. Led interpretational talks for large public and private groups, developed a "Junior Ranger" program for local youth organizations, and assisted in the construction and maintenance of refuge facilities.

#### STUDENT RESEARCHER, UNIVERSITY OF MONTANA

University of Montana, Missoula

10/2007 - 05/2009

Developed and maintained active field sites for soil and water sample collection in Yellowstone National Park. Gathered GPS data using a Trimble Pathfinder PRO unit, analyzed data and developed drainage maps. Analyzed hard-rock samples with XRD and SEM technology. Established a stable field site for a three-moth monitoring project, maintained hydrological equipment, and gathered data at the field site.

## **EDUCATION** MASTER OF SCIENCE, GIS

University of Denver, Denver, CO

Current

**GIS CERTIFICATE** 

 ${\it University of Denver, Denver, CO}$ 

08/2014

**BACHELOR OF SCIENCE, GEOLOGY** 

University of Montana, Missoula, MT

05/2009

#### CERTIFICATIONS 40-hour OSHA HAZWOPER

8-hour First Aid/First Responder

# AWARDS AND National Science Foundation Research Grant

SCHOLARHIPS Women in Geosciences Scholarship

Robert and Eleanor Weidman Geoscience Research Scholarship

First Place in the Physical Sciences Division at the University of Montana

Conference for Undergraduate Research.

## PUBLICATIONS "The Story Beneath Your Feet in the Firehole River" ISUU Online Journal,

1/15/14

Issuu.com Article